<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Unseen-Species on Folgert Karsdorp</title>
    <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/unseen-species/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Unseen-Species on Folgert Karsdorp</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Folgert Karsdorp; made with Hugo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 09:03:02 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/unseen-species/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Unseen Shared Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 09:03:02 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;shared-species-estimation&#34;&gt;Shared Species Estimation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/&#34;&gt;Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing&lt;/a&gt;, I tried to explain the intuition behind the Chao1&#xA;estimator (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_1&#34;&gt;Chao 1984&lt;/a&gt;) for unseen species using the&#xA;Good-Turing estimator as described in Chao et al. (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_2&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;). The&#xA;latter article discusses another set of diversity measures within that same framework of&#xA;Turing. The number of unique species or the number of unique cultural artifacts in a given&#xA;environment is only one diversity measure, but we can also study the shared diversity&#xA;between two cultural collections, for example. In addition to the number of unique&#xA;species, this definition of diversity thus also involves the specific composition of an&#xA;assemblage or collection. As with estimating the number of unique species, it is quite&#xA;conceivable that our samples do not give a complete picture of which species or cultural&#xA;artifacts are shared between two assemblages or collections. Fortunately, with only a few&#xA;small adjustments, we can modify the Good-Turing framework to compute a lower-bound on the&#xA;number of unseen items &lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt; between two collections.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zelterman&#39;s Estimator of Population Size</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 12:43:51 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;zelterman-s-estimator&#34;&gt;Zelterman&amp;rsquo;s Estimator&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/&#34;&gt;Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced and explained the &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Chao1 estimator&lt;/a&gt; as&#xA;an example of a well-known model for estimating the number of unseen species. In this&#xA;notebook, I study some aspects of another, alternative estimator developed in&#xA;Zelterman (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_5&#34;&gt;1988&lt;/a&gt;), which has been popular in applications&#xA;such as drug user studies. This estimator has particular properties that make it more&#xA;robust or less sensitive to violations of the underlying model. As such, it would be&#xA;interesting to study how well the estimator performs when applied to cultural data. In&#xA;what follows, I base my descriptions on the original paper by&#xA;Zelterman (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_5&#34;&gt;1988&lt;/a&gt;) as well as the more recent application of&#xA;the method by Böhning and van der Heijden (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_1&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
