<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Folgert Karsdorp</title>
    <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Folgert Karsdorp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Folgert Karsdorp; made with Hugo and Org-mode</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 15:12:17 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Explorers and Exploiters: Deviations from Rarefaction Curves</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231219152440-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 15:12:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231219152440-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</guid>
      <description>This notebook is the second in of a series of notebooks based on a talk I gave at the CUDAN 2023 conference in Tallinn, Estonia (https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/) together with Melvin Wevers and Mike Kestemont, titled Steady Formulas, Shifting Spells: Estimating Folktale Diversity.
Collector&amp;rsquo;s curves In a previous discussion, I delved into how we can use ecological concepts to understand cultural diversity, focusing on what we call &amp;lsquo;cultural richness.&amp;rsquo; This term refers to the variety of unique items found in different collections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coverage-based Comparisons of Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 11:23:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</guid>
      <description>This notebook is the first of a series of notebooks based on a talk I gave at the CUDAN 2023 conference in Tallinn, Estonia (https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/) together with Melvin Wevers and Mike Kestemont, titled Steady Formulas, Shifting Spells: Estimating Folktale Diversity.
Comparing Cultural Diversity Estimates Quantifying the diversity of cultural collections presents many unique challenges. In earlier posts (e.g., Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing and Population Size Estimation as a Regression Problem), I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed the issue of undersampling in cultural collections, largely as a consequence of cultural loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unseen Crime Simulation</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20230425123401-unseen_crime_simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 15:59:36 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20230425123401-unseen_crime_simulation/</guid>
      <description>Motivation In a recent set of experiments, we aim to use Unseen Species Models such as the Chao1 estimator (see Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing) to correct for biases in historical criminology data. Specifically, we aim to estimate the true number of criminals active during a particular year in 19th century Brussels and Antwerp. For these experiments, we rely on police reports, which list the apprensions of individuals at different moments in time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Literate Emacs Configuration</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/dotemacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 17:08:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/dotemacs/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s this? This document is a literate version of my GNU Emacs configuration written in Org mode. Org mode is a kind of markdown with super powers, which allows you to write code side by side with the corresponding documentation. My Emacs configuration is the result of certainly years and years of tinkering and refinement, and there is always something that could be just a little bit better or different so that it fits my workflow better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Shall We Do with the Unseen Sailor?</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 19:59:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</guid>
      <description>Bias in historical records At the Computational Humanities Research conference 2022 held in Antwerp from December 12 to 14, I co-presented a new paper with Melvin Wevers on missing data in historical archives. The paper was pubslished with CEUR-WS and can be found here: https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper1793.pdf. Missing data is rather the norm than the exception in historical archives. There are virtually endless reasons why records did not survive the test of time: they might have been lost due to natural causes, such as fires, decisions on the level of archival policy making, but also due to content production biases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Diversity as a Generalization of Lexical Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220926232754-lexical_diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 16:58:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220926232754-lexical_diversity/</guid>
      <description>This is a transcript of a talk given at the CHR2022 conference. For the corresponding paper, see https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper2780.pdf.
 Lexical diversity One of the simplest and most basic corpus statistics is the number of unique words in a text. This number gives us a quick and straightforward picture of the lexical diversity of a text. Lexical diversity is typically implemented by measuring the number of unique letter combinations. This is of course very easy to do, but it doesn’t necessarily describe the lexical richness of a text adequately.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Undetected Functional Attribute Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220610145347-undetected_functional_diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 12:31:36 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220610145347-undetected_functional_diversity/</guid>
      <description>Functional Diversity In some previous notebooks (see, for example, here, here, and here), I have discussed the concept of cultural diversity and how methods from ecology can be used to estimate the lower bound of unseen cultural diversity. In these notebooks, diversity was understood simply as the number of unique items in a collection (e.g., species, narratives, pictures, melodies, etc.), with all elements being considered as equidistant, or, in other words, categorically different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Unseen Shared Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 09:03:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</guid>
      <description>Shared Species Estimation In Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing, I tried to explain the intuition behind the Chao1 estimator (Chao 1984) for unseen species using the Good-Turing estimator as described in Chao et al. (2017). The latter article discusses another set of diversity measures within that same framework of Turing. The number of unique species or the number of unique cultural artifacts in a given environment is only one diversity measure, but we can also study the shared diversity between two cultural collections, for example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Population Size Estimation as a Regression Problem</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405110456-population_size_regression_estimators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 09:37:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405110456-population_size_regression_estimators/</guid>
      <description>Unseen heterogeneity Unseen Species Models such as Chao1 provide accurate point-estimates of the population size when the rare species in studied sample are homogeneous. That is, in the case of animal species, for example, all species are equally likely to be observed. Of course, this is a simplifying assumption. Some species are simply more difficult to spot than others, and so most samples contain unseen heterogeneity. When such heterogeneity is present in a sample, the Chao1 estimate reduces to a lower bound of the actual population size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zelterman&#39;s Estimator of Population Size</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 12:43:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</guid>
      <description>Zelterman&amp;rsquo;s Estimator In Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing, I introduced and explained the Chao1 estimator as an example of a well-known model for estimating the number of unseen species. In this notebook, I study some aspects of another, alternative estimator developed in Zelterman (1988), which has been popular in applications such as drug user studies. This estimator has particular properties that make it more robust or less sensitive to violations of the underlying model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Richness under Sampling without Replacement</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220323122150-estimating_richness_under_sampling_without_replacement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 12:35:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220323122150-estimating_richness_under_sampling_without_replacement/</guid>
      <description>Unseen Species Models such as Chao1 assume that the sample being studied was created with replacement. This means that calculations are based on the assumption that certain individuals can or have been repeatedly observed. It also implies that the observation of one individual does not influence the observation of the next individual. That is to say: observations are independent. Take, for example, an ecologist who wants to use Chao1 to estimate the number of unique animal species that live in a given environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/</guid>
      <description>To estimate the &amp;ldquo;biodiversity&amp;rdquo; in a particular area &amp;ndash; or, in other words, the number of unique species living in a given environment &amp;ndash; ecologists usually have no other option than to rely on incomplete samples. For all sorts of practical reasons, it is virtually impossible to spot all species that are actually present in an area, and hence certain species will be missing in the counts. Consequently, an important research question in ecology is how to reliably estimate the resulting &amp;ldquo;bias&amp;rdquo; between the number of species that was observerd and the true number of unique species in an area.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
