<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>folktales on Folgert Karsdorp</title>
    <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/folktales/</link>
    <description>Recent content in folktales on Folgert Karsdorp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Folgert Karsdorp; made with Hugo and Org-mode</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 15:12:17 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/folktales/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Explorers and Exploiters: Deviations from Rarefaction Curves</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231219152440-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 15:12:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231219152440-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</guid>
      <description>This notebook is the second in of a series of notebooks based on a talk I gave at the CUDAN 2023 conference in Tallinn, Estonia (https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/) together with Melvin Wevers and Mike Kestemont, titled Steady Formulas, Shifting Spells: Estimating Folktale Diversity.
Collector&amp;rsquo;s curves In a previous discussion, I delved into how we can use ecological concepts to understand cultural diversity, focusing on what we call &amp;lsquo;cultural richness.&amp;rsquo; This term refers to the variety of unique items found in different collections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coverage-based Comparisons of Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 11:23:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</guid>
      <description>This notebook is the first of a series of notebooks based on a talk I gave at the CUDAN 2023 conference in Tallinn, Estonia (https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/) together with Melvin Wevers and Mike Kestemont, titled Steady Formulas, Shifting Spells: Estimating Folktale Diversity.
Comparing Cultural Diversity Estimates Quantifying the diversity of cultural collections presents many unique challenges. In earlier posts (e.g., Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing and Population Size Estimation as a Regression Problem), I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed the issue of undersampling in cultural collections, largely as a consequence of cultural loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Unseen Shared Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 09:03:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</guid>
      <description>Shared Species Estimation In Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing, I tried to explain the intuition behind the Chao1 estimator (Chao 1984) for unseen species using the Good-Turing estimator as described in Chao et al. (2017). The latter article discusses another set of diversity measures within that same framework of Turing. The number of unique species or the number of unique cultural artifacts in a given environment is only one diversity measure, but we can also study the shared diversity between two cultural collections, for example.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
