<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bias on Folgert Karsdorp</title>
    <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/bias/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bias on Folgert Karsdorp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Folgert Karsdorp; made with Hugo and Org-mode</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 11:23:27 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/bias/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Coverage-based Comparisons of Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 11:23:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</guid>
      <description>This notebook is the first of a series of notebooks based on a talk I gave at the CUDAN 2023 conference in Tallinn, Estonia (https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/) together with Melvin Wevers and Mike Kestemont, titled Steady Formulas, Shifting Spells: Estimating Folktale Diversity.
Comparing Cultural Diversity Estimates Quantifying the diversity of cultural collections presents many unique challenges. In earlier posts (e.g., Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing and Population Size Estimation as a Regression Problem), I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed the issue of undersampling in cultural collections, largely as a consequence of cultural loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Shall We Do with the Unseen Sailor?</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 19:59:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</guid>
      <description>Bias in historical records At the Computational Humanities Research conference 2022 held in Antwerp from December 12 to 14, I co-presented a new paper with Melvin Wevers on missing data in historical archives. The paper was pubslished with CEUR-WS and can be found here: https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper1793.pdf. Missing data is rather the norm than the exception in historical archives. There are virtually endless reasons why records did not survive the test of time: they might have been lost due to natural causes, such as fires, decisions on the level of archival policy making, but also due to content production biases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Undetected Functional Attribute Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220610145347-undetected_functional_diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 12:31:36 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220610145347-undetected_functional_diversity/</guid>
      <description>Functional Diversity In some previous notebooks (see, for example, here, here, and here), I have discussed the concept of cultural diversity and how methods from ecology can be used to estimate the lower bound of unseen cultural diversity. In these notebooks, diversity was understood simply as the number of unique items in a collection (e.g., species, narratives, pictures, melodies, etc.), with all elements being considered as equidistant, or, in other words, categorically different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Richness under Sampling without Replacement</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220323122150-estimating_richness_under_sampling_without_replacement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 12:35:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220323122150-estimating_richness_under_sampling_without_replacement/</guid>
      <description>Unseen Species Models such as Chao1 assume that the sample being studied was created with replacement. This means that calculations are based on the assumption that certain individuals can or have been repeatedly observed. It also implies that the observation of one individual does not influence the observation of the next individual. That is to say: observations are independent. Take, for example, an ecologist who wants to use Chao1 to estimate the number of unique animal species that live in a given environment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
