<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diversity on Folgert Karsdorp</title>
    <link>http://localhost:60738/tags/diversity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Diversity on Folgert Karsdorp</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Folgert Karsdorp; made with Hugo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 20:51:29 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:60738/tags/diversity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Explorers and Exploiters: Deviations from Rarefaction Curves</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20231219152440-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20231219152440-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This notebook is the second in a series of notebooks based on a talk I gave&#xA;at the CUDAN 2023 conference in Tallinn, Estonia&#xA;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/&#34;&gt;https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/&lt;/a&gt;) together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.melvinwevers.nl&#34;&gt;Melvin Wevers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://mikekestemont.github.io/&#34;&gt;Mike&#xA;Kestemont&lt;/a&gt;, titled &lt;em&gt;Steady Formulas, Shifting Spells: Estimating Folktale&#xA;Diversity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;collector-s-curves&#34;&gt;Collector&amp;rsquo;s curves&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:60738/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/&#34;&gt;previous discussion&lt;/a&gt;, I delved into how we can use ecological concepts to&#xA;understand &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;cultural diversity&lt;/a&gt;, focusing on what we call &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;cultural richness&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;This term refers to the variety of unique items found in different collections.&#xA;I illustrated the use of a method developed by&#xA;Chao and Jost (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_1&#34;&gt;2012&lt;/a&gt;) to compare this richness across&#xA;collections in a way that doesn’t depend on how much effort the collectors put&#xA;into gathering their items. This method is based on estimates of the &amp;ldquo;coverage&amp;rdquo;&#xA;of a collection (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_2&#34;&gt;Good 1953&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coverage-based Comparisons of Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 11:23:27 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20231218135129-explorers_and_exploiters_mapping_search_strategies_of_folktale_collectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This notebook is the first of a series of notebooks based on a talk I gave at&#xA;the CUDAN 2023 conference in Tallinn, Estonia (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/&#34;&gt;https://cudan.tlu.ee/conference/&lt;/a&gt;)&#xA;together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.melvinwevers.nl&#34;&gt;Melvin Wevers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://mikekestemont.github.io/&#34;&gt;Mike Kestemont&lt;/a&gt;, titled &lt;em&gt;Steady Formulas,&#xA;Shifting Spells: Estimating Folktale Diversity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparing-cultural-diversity-estimates&#34;&gt;Comparing Cultural Diversity Estimates&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Quantifying the diversity of cultural collections presents many unique&#xA;challenges. In earlier posts (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:60738/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/&#34;&gt;Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing&lt;/a&gt; and&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:60738/posts/20220405110456-population_size_regression_estimators/&#34;&gt;Population Size Estimation as a Regression Problem&lt;/a&gt;), I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed the issue of&#xA;undersampling in cultural collections, largely as a consequence of cultural&#xA;loss. In this post, I discuss some problems when &lt;em&gt;comparing&lt;/em&gt; diversity&#xA;measurements: When and how can we assert that one collection is more diverse&#xA;than another?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Shall We Do with the Unseen Sailor?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 19:59:23 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bias-in-historical-records&#34;&gt;Bias in historical records&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&#34;https://2022.computational-humanities-research.org&#34;&gt;Computational Humanities Research conference 2022&lt;/a&gt; held in Antwerp from December 12&#xA;to 14, I co-presented a new paper with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.melvinwevers.nl/&#34;&gt;Melvin Wevers&lt;/a&gt; on missing data in historical&#xA;archives. The paper was pubslished with CEUR-WS and can be found here:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper1793.pdf&#34;&gt;https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper1793.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. Missing data is rather the norm than the&#xA;exception in historical archives. There are virtually endless reasons why records did not&#xA;survive the test of time: they might have been lost due to natural causes, such as fires,&#xA;decisions on the level of archival policy making, but also due to content production&#xA;biases. When working with incomplete data archives, we run into all kinds of risk, such as&#xA;overestimating the impact of specific historical events, misrepresenting class, and&#xA;underestimating casualties. For this reason, we need to critically evaluate whether the&#xA;data we are left with is representative of the archival collection or historical period&#xA;from which its stems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional Diversity as a Generalization of Lexical Diversity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220926232754-lexical_diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 16:58:56 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220926232754-lexical_diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a transcript of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/z8OCu9tB-jY&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; given at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://2022.computational-humanities-research.org&#34;&gt;CHR2022&lt;/a&gt; conference. For the corresponding&#xA;paper, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper2780.pdf&#34;&gt;https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper2780.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/z8OCu9tB-jY&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;lexical-diversity&#34;&gt;Lexical diversity&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the simplest and most basic corpus statistics is the number of unique words in a&#xA;text. This number gives us a quick and straightforward picture of the lexical diversity of&#xA;a text. Lexical diversity is typically implemented by measuring the number of unique&#xA;letter combinations. This is of course very easy to do, but it doesn’t necessarily&#xA;describe the lexical richness of a text adequately. This becomes clear when we compare the&#xA;following few sets of words:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undetected Functional Attribute Diversity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220610145347-undetected_functional_diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 12:31:36 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220610145347-undetected_functional_diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;functional-diversity&#34;&gt;Functional Diversity&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In some previous notebooks (see, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:60738/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:60738/posts/20220323122150-estimating_richness_under_sampling_without_replacement/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:60738/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), I have discussed the&#xA;concept of cultural diversity and how methods from ecology can be used to estimate the&#xA;lower bound of unseen cultural diversity. In these notebooks, diversity was understood&#xA;simply as the number of unique items in a collection (e.g., species, narratives, pictures,&#xA;melodies, etc.), with all elements being considered as equidistant, or, in other words,&#xA;categorically different. Of course, it only rarely, if ever, happens that all items are&#xA;exactly equally different from each other. It is much more likely that some species are&#xA;more similar than others. And the same is true of cultural artefacts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Population Size Estimation as a Regression Problem</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220405110456-population_size_regression_estimators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 09:37:34 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220405110456-population_size_regression_estimators/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;unseen-heterogeneity&#34;&gt;Unseen heterogeneity&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Unseen Species Model&lt;/a&gt;s such as &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Chao1&lt;/a&gt; provide accurate point-estimates of the population&#xA;size when the rare species in studied sample are homogeneous. That is, in the case of&#xA;animal species, for example, all species are equally likely to be observed. Of course,&#xA;this is a simplifying assumption. Some species are simply more difficult to spot than&#xA;others, and so most samples contain unseen heterogeneity. When such heterogeneity is&#xA;present in a sample, the Chao1 estimate reduces to a lower bound of the actual population&#xA;size. What happens when we do have knowledge about (some parts of) the the origin of the&#xA;heterogeneity? Is there a way to use that information to correct for some of the bias of&#xA;Chao&amp;rsquo;s estimator?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zelterman&#39;s Estimator of Population Size</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 12:43:51 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;zelterman-s-estimator&#34;&gt;Zelterman&amp;rsquo;s Estimator&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:60738/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/&#34;&gt;Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced and explained the &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Chao1 estimator&lt;/a&gt; as&#xA;an example of a well-known model for estimating the number of unseen species. In this&#xA;notebook, I study some aspects of another, alternative estimator developed in&#xA;Zelterman (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_5&#34;&gt;1988&lt;/a&gt;), which has been popular in applications&#xA;such as drug user studies. This estimator has particular properties that make it more&#xA;robust or less sensitive to violations of the underlying model. As such, it would be&#xA;interesting to study how well the estimator performs when applied to cultural data. In&#xA;what follows, I base my descriptions on the original paper by&#xA;Zelterman (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_5&#34;&gt;1988&lt;/a&gt;) as well as the more recent application of&#xA;the method by Böhning and van der Heijden (&lt;a href=&#34;#citeproc_bib_item_1&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:60738/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To estimate the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;biodiversity&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; in a particular area &amp;ndash; or, in other words, the number of&#xA;unique species living in a given environment &amp;ndash; ecologists usually have no other option&#xA;than to rely on incomplete samples. For all sorts of practical reasons, it is virtually&#xA;impossible to spot all species that are actually present in an area, and hence certain&#xA;species will be missing in the counts. Consequently, an important research question in&#xA;ecology is how to reliably estimate the resulting &amp;ldquo;bias&amp;rdquo; between the number of species&#xA;that was observerd and the true number of unique species in an area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
