<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>chao1 on Folgert Karsdorp</title>
    <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/chao1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in chao1 on Folgert Karsdorp</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Folgert Karsdorp; made with Hugo and Org-mode</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 19:59:23 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.karsdorp.io/tags/chao1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What Shall We Do with the Unseen Sailor?</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 19:59:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20221215175357-what_shall_we_do_with_the_unseen_sailor/</guid>
      <description>Bias in historical records At the Computational Humanities Research conference 2022 held in Antwerp from December 12 to 14, I co-presented a new paper with Melvin Wevers on missing data in historical archives. The paper was pubslished with CEUR-WS and can be found here: https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3290/short_paper1793.pdf. Missing data is rather the norm than the exception in historical archives. There are virtually endless reasons why records did not survive the test of time: they might have been lost due to natural causes, such as fires, decisions on the level of archival policy making, but also due to content production biases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Unseen Shared Cultural Diversity</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 09:03:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220316142536-two_assemblage_good_turing_estimation/</guid>
      <description>Shared Species Estimation In Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing, I tried to explain the intuition behind the Chao1 estimator (Chao 1984) for unseen species using the Good-Turing estimator as described in Chao et al. (2017). The latter article discusses another set of diversity measures within that same framework of Turing. The number of unique species or the number of unique cultural artifacts in a given environment is only one diversity measure, but we can also study the shared diversity between two cultural collections, for example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Population Size Estimation as a Regression Problem</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405110456-population_size_regression_estimators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 09:37:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405110456-population_size_regression_estimators/</guid>
      <description>Unseen heterogeneity Unseen Species Models such as Chao1 provide accurate point-estimates of the population size when the rare species in studied sample are homogeneous. That is, in the case of animal species, for example, all species are equally likely to be observed. Of course, this is a simplifying assumption. Some species are simply more difficult to spot than others, and so most samples contain unseen heterogeneity. When such heterogeneity is present in a sample, the Chao1 estimate reduces to a lower bound of the actual population size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zelterman&#39;s Estimator of Population Size</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 12:43:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220405102342-zelterman_estimator/</guid>
      <description>Zelterman&amp;rsquo;s Estimator In Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing, I introduced and explained the Chao1 estimator as an example of a well-known model for estimating the number of unseen species. In this notebook, I study some aspects of another, alternative estimator developed in Zelterman (1988), which has been popular in applications such as drug user studies. This estimator has particular properties that make it more robust or less sensitive to violations of the underlying model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Richness under Sampling without Replacement</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220323122150-estimating_richness_under_sampling_without_replacement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 12:35:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220323122150-estimating_richness_under_sampling_without_replacement/</guid>
      <description>Unseen Species Models such as Chao1 assume that the sample being studied was created with replacement. This means that calculations are based on the assumption that certain individuals can or have been repeatedly observed. It also implies that the observation of one individual does not influence the observation of the next individual. That is to say: observations are independent. Take, for example, an ecologist who wants to use Chao1 to estimate the number of unique animal species that live in a given environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying Chao1 with Good-Turing</title>
      <link>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.karsdorp.io/posts/20220309103709-good_turing_as_an_unseen_species_model/</guid>
      <description>To estimate the &amp;ldquo;biodiversity&amp;rdquo; in a particular area &amp;ndash; or, in other words, the number of unique species living in a given environment &amp;ndash; ecologists usually have no other option than to rely on incomplete samples. For all sorts of practical reasons, it is virtually impossible to spot all species that are actually present in an area, and hence certain species will be missing in the counts. Consequently, an important research question in ecology is how to reliably estimate the resulting &amp;ldquo;bias&amp;rdquo; between the number of species that was observerd and the true number of unique species in an area.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
